Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/john-brazzale-1948806 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Credit
Commercial Lending
Commercial Banking

John Brazzale

Chief Strategy, Marketing & Administrative Officer, Corporate Banking - Northern Trust

Chicago, Illinois

Summary

Depth and breadth of experiences result in the ability to see opportunities in all situations and a willingness to take the right risks to achieve goals. Leading organic growth initiatives, divestitures and through financial crises, focusing on people, staff and clients, globally, have driven success. A keen interest in the intersection of data to inform strategy, new product development and execution. Innovation through culture change and adopting technology has been key to driving efficiency. The result, the ability to recognize, adapt and lead change through innovation, financial discipline and operational efficiency.

Experience

Bridge Advisors Chief Executive Officer 2020 - Present (less than a year) Chicago and San Francisco

Advisor to executives and boards of directors on topics including strategy, leadership development, organizational structure, financial and operational management and governance. For profit and not for profits organizations focusing on business growth, turnarounds and workouts.

Client 1 - Advisor; Board of Directors & Interim CEO - Brought in to assess operating model, business strategy, financial profile and leadership.

Recommendations resulting in shifts to brand strategies, executive changes, realignment of resources and changes in financial management. Currently developing the five year strategic plan to build out brands, delivery platforms, organizational model required to support it and board governance.

Client 2 - Advisor; Board of Directors - Assist with development of strategy for what the board structure and member profile should look like to support a strategic plan of double digit growth. Implement governance and board

structures future members would expect in a a similar organization. Developing board leadership and growth program.

Northern Trust Company

Chief Strategy, Marketing & Administrative Officer; Corporate Banking Services

2014 - 2019 (5 years)

Executive responsible for Strategy, Marketing, Administration, Product Management, Non Credit Risk Management and Business Development initiatives across four global institutional banking businesses.

- 1. Manage strategy project focused on client profitability, use of capital, organizational structure, business development and staffing efficiency.
- a. Identify / implement opportunities to reduce direct expenses up to 30%, allocated capital 12% and increase BU profitability 11%.
- 2. Manage strategy project focused on increasing capital investment, refocusing client retention and prioritizing product development in one business.
- a. Results in management group support for 60% increase in capital, 10% increase in new business opportunities and institutional support for client retention strategies.
- 3. Manage BU activities focused on analyzing and implementing changes in operations, including automation and shift of work to Bangalore India.
- a. Operating efficiencies equal to support business growth reducing need to grow staff by 25%
- b. Hire staff and transfer functions to Bangalore Expanded FTE by 150% with no expense increase.
- c. Future opportunities identified address staff concentration issues reducing direct expenses 80%
- 4. Manage vendor relationships and coordination with Corporate Procurement
- a. Standardize review and acquisition of contracts / services
- b. Consolidate management of expenses across 4 businesses, 4 geographies and 12 vendors
- c. Reduce expenses 9% by eliminating duplicative services and contract renegotiation
- Member of cross business unit management teams focused on analyses, execution and metrics to increase market penetration and business opportunities for strategic product sales initiatives
- 6. Manage development, implementation and expansion of mobile technologies focused on cost reductions of 15%

7. Take on added responsibility for regulatory compliance including Basel and Dodd Frank

Northern Trust

SVP & Chief Marketing Officer - Corporate Banking Services 2010 - 2013 (3 years)

Increasing responsibility for five institutional banking related businesses. Includes Strategy, Marketing, cross business unit sales initiatives, staff training, PMO for corporate and business unit initiatives, non credit risk management and product management.

- 1. Cross sell strategies lead to revenue increases consistently 90% greater than when group was created
- 2. Leverage previously developed communications, reporting and performance metrics across expanded group of external and internal stakeholder groups.
- 3. Develop, implement and manage performance scorecards for all levels of staff and management.
- 4. Reduce quarterly reporting cycles 300% by standardizing and automating processes.
- 5. Manage cross business unit sales management / communication forums to increase staff engagement.
- 6. Manage 10 teams focused on increasing staff engagement / satisfaction.
- 7. Lead changes required to remediate operating issues identified in internal audits.
- 8. Lead annual review of management / staff expectations to ensure alignment with strategy.
- 9. Oversee analyses of tax law changes resulted in 8% increase in cross border lending to foreign subsidiaries of US multinationals.
- 10. Manage analyses of industry / sector dynamics that affect extension of credit exposure to clients results lead to 15% annual increase in lending to these sectors.
- 11. Lead development of first external / internal digital marketing strategies for the five businesses.

Northern Trust Company

SVP & Chief Marketing Officer - Credit Products Group 2006 - September 2009 (3 years)

Responsible for coordination of sales and marketing activities, staff development and cross business unit coordination of sales for the corporate, insurance and not for profit segments of the US lending business.

- 1. Develop and manage communications program for external stakeholders (clients and vendors) and internal partners including executive management).
- 2. Develop and implement key metrics for measuring success and changes in the business.
- 3. Implement new business strategies resulting in 10% annual growth in new clients and revenues.
- 4. Implement staff training focused on skill development and product knowledge to drive business growth.
- 5. Develop metrics for measuring staff performance.
- 6. Manage group reporting function.

Northern Trust Company VP / Senior Banker 2000 - 2005 (5 years)

Responsible for client portfolio and business development in Western US. Manage credit / non credit relationships, selling all institutional services available to clients:

- 1. Grow client portfolio 10% annually
- 2. Successfully manage credit portfolio with zero credit losses
- 3. Participated in development of first multi currency investment capability for an institutional client
- 4. Grew assets under management in the portfolio by 4,000% to over \$3B
- 5. Generate \$1.25MM in new business annually during tenure
- 6. Increase product penetration in portfolio from average of 1.2 to 3.4 during tenure
- 7. Generate average of 3 new clients per year during tenure.

Northern Trust Company VP / Treasury Consultant 1993 - 1999 (6 years)

- Consult with clients / prospects to evaluate strategy / changes for treasury / finance and related operations.
- Completed 65 projects with clients (revenue size \$500MM \$20B) across 12 industries.
- * Grew client portfolio 15% annually
- ** Increased revenues 18% annually
- *** Never lost an existing client
- 1. Assist clients with evaluation of processing, technology and automating and outsourcing bank services and internal accounting activities.

- 2. Work closely with clients to evaluate / execute re-engineering and outsourcing alternatives
- 3. Develop framework to determine impact of strategic technology initiatives including ERP systems and internet technology for clients / prospects.
- 4. Developed financial model to assist clients / prospects evaluate funding alternatives for commercial paper and medium term notes.
- 5. Participate in business justification, financial modeling, market and risk assessments for product development of new services identified through consulting engagements.
- 6. Recognized industry expert spoke at over 90 conferences and published 12 articles.
- 7. Participated in company's first electronic commerce market strategy leading into the expansion of the internet.

Northern Trust Company

5 years

Product Manager - Treasury Services 1990 - 1992 (2 years)

- * Responsible for P&L, product management / development, , cap ex execution, sales support and regulatory requirements.
- * Increased new client revenues 11% annually, increased other revenues 8% annually through pricing strategies.
- * Developed new capabilities based on client needs / market research
- * Coordinate with operations partners to drive 20% improvement in client satisfaction from imp[roved operating quality.
- * Managed private label bank relationships who delivered services for the product line.

Commercial Banker

1988 - 1990 (2 years)

- * Manage portfolio of 75 clients with annual revenues over \$250MM each across 12 industries.
- * Increased revenue 16% annually, decreased lost business 20% annually.
- * Established credit relationships including trade finance, letters of credit, working capital and commercial paper back up.

Manager - Custody Operations 1987 - 1989 (2 years)

Manage teams responsible for accounting functions, reducing past due backlog by 100% and increasing timeliness of reconcilement activities 75%.

Lead projects to automate two major functions, reducing processing time by 80% and exceptions by 60%.

Education

NYU Stern School of Business
Executive education, Corporate Strategy · (2020 - 2020)

Northwestern University - Kellogg School of Management Executive Education, Finance, Marketing & Leadership

The London School of Economics and Political Science (LSE) Certificate Program, Business Strategy & Government

Western Illinois University Corp. Finance